ALEXIS MARCHAND

address Department of Mathematics, Kyoto University

Kyoto 606-8502, Japan

email marchand.alexis.85h@st.kyoto-u.ac.jp

website alexis-marchand.github.io

RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research is in *geometric group theory*, a field concerned with understanding groups — algebraic structures encoding the symmetries of mathematical objects — by studying their actions on geometric spaces. I am generally interested in understanding connections between group-theoretical structure and *non-positive curvature*.

Keywords: stable commutator length, bounded cohomology, quasimorphisms, topology of surfaces, hyperbolicity, CAT(0) cube complexes, group rings, free group automorphisms.

EMPLOYMENT

²⁰²⁴⁻²⁵ JSPS Postdoctoral Fellow for Research in Japan · Kyoto University

Mentor: Koji Fujiwara

EDUCATION

2021-24 Ph.D. in Pure Mathematics · *University of Cambridge*

Thesis: Computations and lower bounds for scl and the relative Gromov seminorm Supervisor: Henry Wilton

2017-21 Dipl. ENS · École Normale Supérieure de Lyon

2020-21 M.Sc. in Mathematics · *Université Grenoble Alpes*

Mention Très Bien

Thesis: Automorphismes extérieurs de produits libres : revêtements abéliens

caractéristiques et représentations libres

Supervisor: François Dahmani

2019-20 M.A.St. in Mathematics · *University of Cambridge*

Pass with Merit

Essay: Rigidity Theorems for Hyperbolic Groups

Supervisor: Henry Wilton

2017-19 B.Sc. in Mathematics · École Normale Supérieure de Lyon

Research internships:

- Topology of complex affine varieties, with Hossein Movasati in IMPA, Rio de Janeiro (2019)
- Geometry of Coxeter groups, with CATERINA CAMPAGNOLO in KIT, Karlsruhe (2018)

ACCEPTED PAPERS

- [1] Alexis Marchand, From letter-quasimorphisms to angle structures and spectral gaps for scl, 2024. *Israel J. Math.* (to appear). arXiv:2402.13856
- [2] Alexis Marchand, Isometric embeddings of surfaces for scl, 2023. *Groups Geom. Dyn.* (to appear). arXiv:2302.04133
- [3] Alexis Marchand, Bavard duality for the relative Gromov seminorm, 2023. *Enseign. Math.* (online first). DOI:10.4171/lem/1087 · arXiv:2305.02149
- [4] Alexis Marchand, Free representations of outer automorphism groups of free products via characteristic abelian coverings, *J. Group Theory* **26** (2023), no. 2, 399-420. DOI:10.1515/jgth-2021-0154 · arXiv:2107.11230

EXPOSITORY ARTICLES

- [5] Alexis Marchand, Makers of patterns: from Escher to Coxeter, Eureka 66 (2020).
- [6] Alexis Marchand, Géométrie des groupes et courbure négative, *Journal de Mathématiques des Élèves de l'ENS de Lyon* **IV** (2020).

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2021-24 Undergraduate supervisions · Trinity College & Peterhouse College, Cambridge

- Analysis & Topology (IB) 46 contact hours
- Geometry (IB) 34 contact hours
- Linear Algebra (IB) 16 contact hours
- Riemann Surfaces (II) 31 contact hours
- 2024 Part III examples classes · *University of Cambridge*

Teaching assistant for Geometric Group Theory — 8 contact hours

2022-23 Admissions interviews · Christ's College, Cambridge

Co-interviewer for undergraduate admissions in mathematics

2021-23 Part III drop-in sessions · *University of Cambridge*

Drop-in session leader for Group Cohomology, Mapping Class Groups

2019-20 School tutoring · Stimulus, Cambridge

Volunteer tutor in mathematics in secondary schools

2018-19 Colles · Lycée Aux Lazaristes, Lyon

Oral examiner in mathematics for first-year students in a preparatory class — 44 contact hours

2017-21 French as a foreign language · ItinérENS, Lyon

Volunteer teacher of French classes for refugees — more than 100 contact hours

ORGANISATIONAL EXPERIENCE

2023-24 Junior geometry seminar · *University of Cambridge*

Co-organiser of the graduate students' seminar in geometry

2023-24 BA computing · Trinity College, Cambridge

MCR committee member in charge of: the MCR's website, mailing list, elections, lunchtime seminars, etc.

2022 Reading seminar · *University of Cambridge*

Organiser of a reading seminar on generalisations of hyperbolic groups

AWARDS

²⁰²³ Smith–Knight & Rayleigh–Knight prize · *University of Cambridge* Grade 3, for the essay *Isometric embeddings of surfaces for scl*

2021 EPSRC PhD studentship · University of Cambridge

Three-year studentship funded by the Engineering & Physical Sciences Research Council

2017 ENS studentship · École Normale Supérieure de Lyon

Four-year studentship with civil servant status funded by the French government

INVITED TALKS

Nov. 2024 First MMS workshop for young researchers · Kyoto University

Nov. 2024 Séminaire virtuel francophone groupes et géométrie · Online

May 2024 Seminari dei baby geometri · Università di Pisa / Scuola Normale Superiore

Apr. 2024 International young seminar on bounded cohomology & simplicial

volume · Online

Apr. 2024 Geometry and geometric analysis seminar · Purdue University (online)

Mar. 2024 Geometric group theory seminar · University of Oxford

Dec. 2023 Bristol junior geometry seminar · University of Bristol

Jun. 2023 International young seminar on bounded cohomology & simplicial

volume · Online

Apr. 2023 Methusalem junior seminar · KU Leuven

Mar. 2023 Geometry graduate colloquium · ETH Zürich

Feb. 2023 Junior topology & group theory seminar · University of Oxford

Feb. 2023 Geometric group theory seminar · University of Cambridge

Jun. 2022 Séminaire compréhensible · Université Grenoble Alpes

Apr. 2022 Séminaire des doctorants de St-Charles · Aix-Marseille Université

CONFERENCES ATTENDED

Apr. 2024 Groups, topology, & applications Gran Bilbao · Euskal Herriko Unibertsitatea

Mar. 2024 Topological & homological methods in group theory · Universität Bielefeld

Feb. 2024 GAGTA · CIRM, Marseille

Contributed talk & poster

Jul. 2023 Postgraduate group theory conference · Heriot-Watt University, Edinburgh Contributed talk

May 2023 Geometry of subgroups · CRM, Montréal

Jan. 2023 LMS regional meeting · University of Southampton
Contributed poster

Sep. 2022 Recent advances in bounded cohomology · Universität Regensburg

Jun. 2022 Hyperbolic groups and their generalisations · IHP, Paris

Apr. 2022 Mapping class groups and Out (F_n) · *IHP, Paris*

Apr. 2022 Groups acting on fractals · CIRM, Marseille

Feb. 2022 Workshop on finiteness properties · KIT, Karlsruhe

LANGUAGES

French	Native speaker	Portuguese	Advanced (B2)
English	Fluent (C2). Passed the CAE	Russian	Intermediate (B1)
GERMAN	Advanced (B2)	Japanese	Elementary (A2)

September 24, 2024